if you are interested in the new way of making
movements and all kinds of automated stuff in
the GrandMA 3 console this tutorial is for
you we are going to dig into the phaser which
is the new effect engine on the GrandMA it's
kind of different it's very different from the
old one on the GrandMA 2 and on the GrandMA 1
i think it has potential but i think the
learning curve can be can be a little steep
so in this tutorial we're going to look at the
the new phaser and try to load some predefined
effects and if you have been looking at the
console and have been trying out the software you
will find that there's no predefined effects there
you have to load them from a macro and we haven't
touched macro in this tutorial series yet so we
are going to do that in this one by loading a
predefined macro which can load some predefined
phase effects it sounds a little bit complicated
but it's really not so if you want to learn more
watch the video all the way to the end and i
will show you some some cool effects as you
can see here i just prepared a new view
i inserted a macro view down here and i
inserted an old preset here if you don't know how
to find the old preset you can i'll just show you
here click on the empty space here go into presets
and select the first one of the all presets
down here same thing you go into the pools
and you find the macro pool you select it and
it's going to open the macros i mean you can do
this in any way you want and remember if you want
to change the view so where you can get more room
on your computer go into i'll just show you here
go into the icon up here go into configure display
and this is going to show you this one here
and you can set the scale if you right click 0.075
and that's going to give you a lot more room to
work with but for the sake of people watching
on smaller devices i'm just going to stay at
one here so we have our macros down here and
we have our old preset here what we need to do
is create a macro and if you haven't worked
with macros before we're going to get into
that that's in another world basically macros
there is many many macros being built that can
do amazing things on the GrandMA  2 and on the
GrandMA  3 as well macros is really really cool
but for now i'm just going to show you a simple
little thing so if you go down here and you right
click it's going to open and say new macro line
and you can go into import if you click import
you can search for phaser like this and you have
a macro which is called import predefined phaser
if you click that one and say import and you just
close the window down it's going to create a new
macro for you here the only thing you have to do
now is to click it when you click it it's gonna
populate the all preset with a bunch of macros
there is i don't know how many 22 macros and
i believe this is going to grow over time and
i'm sure that ma is going to find a different
way of doing this when the software updates
at the at a later point but this is your
all preset and this is your predefined effects
and by the way if you like this video or get
any value out of it please consider liking the
video and maybe even subscribing to the channel
that way you're going to get a notification every
time we upload a new video right now i have my
vipers on right here in cue 1 we built that in a
previous episode and what you need to do here
is you can select your vipers and you can press
one of the effects and it's going to start to do
something and there's a lot of different things
here the first ones are dimmer dimmer effects
and they can do different things with the
different dimmer curves you can have some maybe
if we clear this one you can probably take some
color effects as well where it goes from white to
red and the same here blue to white and
green to white and you can you can when
we get further in this tutorial series i'm going
to show you how to build the effects on your own
but right now if you want to do something then you
can start by working with the predefined effects
if you can go further than this and say we
had some color presets we can do some
if we select the vipers we can do some tilt
we can probably add some pen to it as well
and it's gonna move real slow and then we
can adjust the speed and the size and everything
after that there's a few other things here some
slow fly outs i haven't used this one ever so
let's see if it works yeah it's a it's actually
a fly-in right now uh but that's the way you can
load predefined effects and then you can save them
and modify them and and do whatever so let's try
modifying an effect so if we clear here once again
and let's say okay we want to build a tilt effect
and we want to build a pan effect for instance
we go up into all our vipers here we press the
tilt effect and it starts to work right now it's
doing everything at the same time there's no
phase in between them there's no randomization
or anything but what you can do is go down to
all these buttons down here and choose face and
this is only the tilt parameter working right now
so if you press the tilt parameter and you are
under the phaser menu it's going to ask you what you
need to what you want to do what we could do was
to put on a zero through 360 on it and it's gonna
spread out the pan effect oh sorry
the tilt effect from 0 to 360.
and you can basically do this again and say
okay i want it to be the other way around it's
going to move the other way and there's a lot of
different things you can do in here you can even
say 0 through 360 through 0 and then it's going
to do something like this so there's a lot of
options in here and it's really cool to work with
but it needs if you haven't worked with GrandMA
may before it's the learning curve is pretty steep
but let's try something different here so now
we have our effect moving we want to save it in a
sequence i just closed down all the sequences down
here because we needed the room for the macros we
can close the macro window down again because we
don't need it anymore then we can click this one
and choose our sequences again and say i deleted
the rest of the sequences we only have this master
cue list right now so right now we have all our
vipers we are only working with one parameter
which is the tilt we could save that on a fader
so let's do that we say store and we put it on
this one number 202 so if we clear here we have
our effect running on the sequence number two
right now what we could do say it's very slow
right now so i would like to make it move faster
so if you go into the sequence number two up here
and you right click it i just need to open the
right window here sorry there we go if we right
click hello where are you there you are and then
we go into the settings and we can start playing
with some some speed options in here right now we
don't have a speed master on it so let's do that
let's start by defining a speed master for the
movement so if we go down into this one called 110
and we right click on this one it's there's
nothing in it but we can basically define a
special master to control our movement speed
so if we go down to the master section here
and then we go into speed number one for instance
and we close it down you can see now there's a
fader here but it doesn't do anything there's
no movement no change in the speed whatsoever
so if we go up to the sequence again here and we
go into the settings of the sequence we can choose
speed master down here and here we can choose
speed number one if we close this one down now
and we take this one all the way down you see
the effect stops if we take it all the way up
the effects is much faster if this not is not fast
enough for you you can do something in here you
can go into sequence number two you can go into
edit settings under speed master just below that
one there's a speed scale you can click the speed
scale and multiply it by two if you right click
you can see all the different options you have in
here this one is the first one we had before this
is one to one basically if you right click it you
can divide the speed by four then it moves a lot
slower and the handle here reacts to the division
you made here again you can say i want to multiply
it by two so it moves fast like this and now this
is the fastest it's going to move then you can
take the speed down like this and make it move
real slow so that's very very simple phaser in
a movement phaser let's build another one and
say now this is our movement phaser let's name it
right here we can use our swipey and say label
and we say tilt effect like this let's build a
color effect of some sort or maybe a dimmer
effect let's take all our vipers again
and let's see if we can find something fun here we
have a sinus dimmer curve so if we push that one
it's going to slowly start to pulsate like this
in a sinus curve once again we go down to face
we go into our demo which is the active parameter
right now and we say 0 through -360 for instance
then it starts to move like this then we can say
okay this effect is now the way we want it we can
set the speed if we want we can say it's at 60
beats per minute right now you can turn it up you
can turn it down that's all up to you but let's
say okay this is what we want so we can once again
say oh sorry we need to store and we can put it
maybe here and we can rename it to to sinus effect
there we go and now we have a speedmaster for
our movement down here but we don't have a
speedmaster for our dimmer let's just start
by renaming this one the speed number one
if we go into speed number one and we go into edit
settings it's called speed one we can call it move
speed and now we can identify what is what
let's build the next one and say on this one
we need to right click on this one we go into
our handle and sorry we're going to our object
we choose our master and you can see we changed
the speed one to move speed let's select number
two close this one down go into it again
and say we need this to be dimmer speed
there we go and right now we have stored
our effect over here let's just clear
we have stored our effect right here on our sinus
effect if we take this one up it's going to start
but right now we have no control over the speed
at all so we need to go into the sinus effect here
and we need to go into the settings we need
to go into the speedmaster and we need to
select dimmer speed so now we should be
able to control the dimmer speed here the
way we want it and again if you want to change the
multiplication if you want to make sure that it's
the the the right scale or whatever you want
to call it you can go into your settings again
and you can set your speed scale down here
if you want to so this is a very very basic
tilt effect this is a very basic sinus effect
let's end this with a small color effect
we can just take this one down and it's once again
it's open let me show you another way of doing it
right now we have our predefined effects here we
can build our own which is actually quite easy
let's select all our wipers let's go down to
color let's go to this one down here which is
number one if we write sorry we need to do
something here we need to choose a color let's say
white then we can oh we need to right now i just
selected one parameter this is kind of annoying
that it always does that but it's it's actually
quite beneficial in in other areas we have to
check this one feature which is the entire handle
right here otherwise it's only going to touch the
the green right here so once again we do
this and go into white and then selected
all three of them let's go to step number
two and select maybe a let's just do a blue
and now it starts to work between white and blue
we can just briefly go into phaser here which is
our facer window which we're going to touch
in another episode which which is where you
can really customize your effects right now
we just need to change our demo curve or our
transition from one to the other if we go down to
this small icon down here and you press it you can
see you have a sinus curve here you have like a
sawtooth here or i don't know this one is what
was called a pvm in the GrandMA 2 if you
press this one it's not gonna fade it's it's gonna
go on or off if you choose this one
you can see here it fades between them
if you choose this one it snaps between them so
now we have this one white blue and then we could
go into our face here again and we can offset it
zero through 360 and it's gonna do it like this
and do it with the base color as well so this
is another way of doing an effect this is once
again because we only have the green parameter
then it's going to do this weird stuff here
so if we go into feature again and we offset it
they're going to follow along all of them so be
aware of this link phaser it it's been bugging
me a few times it's really annoying that it's
not always set to the value where you want
it but when you need to split it up between
different values in pan and till for instance and
even in color as well it's quite useful so just
be aware if it does funny stuff that might
be why i hope you enjoyed this tutorial and
please check out one of the other videos linked on
the screen right now and we'll be back next week
with another tutorial on GrandMA 3 and GrandMA  3
programming if you haven't liked the video please
do so and if you want to check out another video
from us and maybe even subscribe to the channel
you are more than welcome to do so but
thank you and see you next time bye bye